So now we come to the duties and
responsibilities of the board.
And here I'm going to be quoting copies
from the Companies and Allied Matters Act section
305 which describes the fiduciary duties of directors.
Who is a fiduciary?
A fiduciary essentially is somebody who is serving
the interests of others other than themselves, meaning
that their own personal interests are always subjugated
to those of the company that they serve
on as directors.
They also are expected to act in good
faith at all times and that duty is
owed primarily to all stakeholders.
I emphasise all stakeholders here because sometimes there's
a sense or a feeling that directors sit
on the board at the pleasure of shareholders.
That is totally incorrect.
Directors, whether they are non-executive directors, independent
executives, are there at the pleasure of all
stakeholders and they owe their duty to all
stakeholders.
And this stakeholder bucket is very large and
continues to grow.
So you have employees, you have regulators, you
have the society as a whole, you have
customers, you have everybody who has a stake.
That's why they're stakeholders.
And sometimes the stake that they have is
not very apparent.
So a civil rights activist, for instance, who
is not a shareholder, who is not an
employee, who is not a creditor of the
company, can feel that the business is providing
whatever service it is at his pleasure.
And so such a person considers themselves to
be a social stakeholder and they believe that
their interest in the company gives that company
the licence to operate.
So as a director on the board of
a company, you have to be alive to
responsibility and acknowledge the fact that that duty
is owed to all stakeholders.
Directors are also expected to be responsible for
delegated authority.
So whilst the board can delegate its powers
to, for instance, management, board committees, the board
remains primarily responsible for such delegated duties.
And it's not an excuse to say, for
instance, that we have a CFO, he's more
responsible for the accounts.
And so if anything goes wrong with the
accounts, we're not responsible.
We delegate responsibly as a board and we
remain responsible for those delegated duties.
Directors are also expected to exercise power only
for proper purpose.
So because directors have such enormous power, they
have to be careful as to how such
power is exercised.
Otherwise, they can be sued for whatever losses
incurred if improperly exercised.
Directors are expected to exercise a level of
care and skill and ask themselves in all
situations, what will a prudent director do in
comparable circumstances?
Also, directors are not expected to make secret
profits, meaning that they shouldn't be involved in
contracts that are not fully disclosed to the
board.
Because directors have access to lots of information
by virtue of their office, they come in
contact with a lot of confidential information, information
that they would otherwise not have come into
contact with.
And this places on them a duty of
confidentiality.
They have to treat corporate information with the
utmost discretion and not share information with non
-members of the board.
One of the most significant responsibilities as well
is the duty not to fetter their discretion.
And to explain this, it means that they
shouldn't pre-agree a position ahead of coming
to a board meeting, for instance.
So if directors are members of a particular,
let's say a venture capital business that has
invested in a company and they have entered
into shareholder agreements that require them to vote
in a particular way, such shareholder agreements might
not stand the scrutiny of this provision because
what it means is that they have pre
-agreed a position which would not allow them
to exercise their discretion in the interest of
the company.
So they are reminded at all times not
to fetter their discretion.
The final responsibility under this head is the
duty to not allow personal interests to conflict
with their responsibilities as directors.
All conflicts of interest have to be disclosed
and not all conflicts of interest can be
cured by disclosure.